@1
The Cathedral
@2
The Crucible. The mansion of Georgiy Kain, Simon Kain's brother
@3
The Crucible. The mansion of Maria Kaina, Victor Kain's daughter
@4
The Crucible. The mansion of Victor Kain, Simon Kain's brother
@5
The Stillwater, Eva Yan's house
@6
The Shelter, Lara Ravel's house
@7
The Trammel, Yulia Lyuricheva's house
@8
The Town Theatre
@9
The Town Hall
@10
The Lump, the Olgimsky's mansion. Home to Big Vlad and Capella
@11
The railway station
@12
The windows of this house are bricked in
@13
The Willows, Anna Angel's house
@14
The Rod, the mansion of Katerina and Alexander Saburov
@15
The Abattoir
@16
The Second Block of the Termitary
@17
The First Block of the Termitary
@18
The Boiler Room
@19
Factory Building #1 (The Old Facility)
@20
Factory Building #2 (The Long Facility)
@21
Factory Building #3 (The Butchering Room)
@22
Factory Building #4 (The Machine)
@23
Grace's Lodge
@24
Peter Stamatin's Studio
@25
Andrey Stamatin's Pub
@26
Bad Grief's Lair
@27
Rubin's Prosectorium
@28
"The Castle of the Soul-and-a-Halves" (the warehouse where the urchins under Chieftain Notkin reside)
@29
The Polyhedron
@30
Aspity's Hospice
@31
Sticky's House
@32
Mishka's Van
@33
Nina Kaina's Tomb
@1000
The butcher is here.