@0
Loading...
@1
Bachelor
@2
Haruspex
@3
Changeling
@4
Day
@5
Price
@6
Loading the world...
@7
Durability:
@8
Boosts immunity: 
@9
Boosts health: 
@10
Increases exhaustion: 
@11
Infection:
@12
DiseaseSpeedRate
@13
Health:
@14
HealthProgress
@15
TirednessIncrease
@16 
Day %d
@17		; Quick save, used in save/load menu
Quick Save
@18		; format string for printing gametime in save files (save/load menu)
Day %d, %d:%02d
@19		; format string for printing savetime in save files (save/load menu)
%d %s, %d:%02d:%02d
@20
January
@21
February
@22
March
@23
April
@24
May
@25
June
@26
July
@27
August
@28
September
@29
October
@30
November
@31
December
@32		; for empty save slot (save menu)
<empty>
@33 key actions
Forward
@34
Backward
@35
Strafe left
@36
Strafe right
@37
Use
@38
Jump
@39
Take a screenshot
@40
Torch
@41
Plaguefinder
@42
Attack
@43
Alt. Attack
@44
Show/hide hands
@45
Inventory
@46
Map
@47
Diary
@48
Letters
@49
Character Status
@50
List of the Bound
@51 
Quit to menu
@52
Quick Save
@53 
Quick Load
@54 
Sneak
@55		
Reload
@56 ; end of key actions
Sheathe/Holster Weapon
@100
Invert Mouse
@101
Mouse Sensitivity
@102
Shadows
@103
Gamma
@104
Master Volume
@105
Music Volume
@106
Voice Volume
@107
Effect Volume
@108
Press the key (ESC to quit)
@109
Saved
@110
Resolution
@111
Anti-aliasing (FXAA)
@112
Anisotropic Filtering
@113
Field of View (FOV)
@114
V-Sync
@115
Depth of Field
@116
SSAO
@117
Bloom
@118
Motion Blur
@119
Please restart the game for the changes to take effect
@120
Gamepad Look Sensitivity
@121
Gamepad UI Sensitivity
@122
Invert Gamepad Look
@123
Gamepad Rumble
@124
Off
@200
Whatever happens, these people must live. Their fates are bound to mine; they may well hold the keys to my victory in their hands.
@201
People are willing to take the fall for reasons most peculiar: cold calculation, despair, duty, and even love... Today a new opportunity to step closer to the victory has come up. Having learned about this, a few people have abandoned the safety of their homes, endeavoring to assist you in your efforts.

If you value their lives, find a way to fulfil your current goal until nightfall. If you couldn't care less, let them do as they please. You have still a few people left who are willing to sacrifice themselves for your cause.
@202
BACHELOR
@203
The history of humanity witnessed a number of catastrophes that have demonstrated without a shadow of a doubt the pettiness of human achievement and the triumph of the invincible Evil. Outbreaks of infectious diseases that have from time to time wiped towns and cities off the map are undoubtedly among those. However smart and virtuous, the people caught up in these destructive events have repeatedly come to the conclusion that it's no use trying to fight these circumstances; the best you can do is bite the bullet and cope with your losses.

This is the story of a person who has managed to work a miracle and defeat a seemingly unvanquishable foe.
@204
THE INVISIBLE ENEMY

Daniil Dankovsky, a Bachelor of Medicine, was brought here by circumstances most unfortunate. Dankovsky's lifework, his theory challenging the existing notions of human mortality, is being harshly persecuted by the Powers That Be. Suddenly, a letter arrives from a colleague, suggesting that there is previously undiscovered evidence which may support Dankovsky's claims.

There is a settlement, the letter says, ruled by an extraordinary man who may well be seen as objective proof of Dankovsky's daring hypothesis. Grasping at straws of hope, Dankovsky decides to follow what he believes to be a sign of divine providence. Without further ado, he sets off for the settlement.

Late at night, the Bachelor arrives in the Town. As he seeks room and board, he gets to know a girl called Eva Yan and stays at her place till dawn.
@205
HARUSPEX
@206
How do they call upon the menkhu, the faithful of a Warden kin? Known by their hands, for they are butchers; known by their eyes, for they are surgeons; they who follow the lines; they who are the leaders of the Kin; they who speak to udurghs; they who know the secret art of haruspicy. What is a haruspex? Reading the future in the entrails, he knows that a body bears semblance to the Universe. His scalpel follows the lines of the body; his steps follow the lines of his kin's fortune. A haruspex that can tell a true line from a false one is entrusted with power. A haruspex who is confused by his path gets buried into the deep black flesh of the Earth.

This is the story of a person who has avoided the contradiction eager to rip a doomed life apart, masterfully fulfilling his true purpose in the process.
@207
SACRIFICE

Artemy Burakh is coming back to his home town after an absence of ten years. Born to a family endowed with a caste right to cut living beings open, he was preparing himself for this line of work since childhood. Artemy's father, Isidor Burakh, a wise man and a philosopher well-respected by the locals, had admitted to the limits of traditional knowledge and sent his son off to study modern medicine in the academy.

Artemy has been travelling from town to town learning theoretical and practical surgery for several years now. Suddenly a mysterious letter appears with his father giving him notice of his impending demise and begging Artemy to return and accept succession. Unwilling to wait for a regular freight train, Artemy follows the rails through the Steppe until he's caught up with by a small shunt locomotive. This is how young Haruspex arrives in the Town.
@208
CHANGELING
@209
Clara had a dream. A foggy morning; having passed a wicket gate, she is now dawdling somewhere, piles of dry leaves rustling in her wake. A familiar voice calls out to her. She lifts her eyes and sees her own twin sister point at an old man convulsing and weeping in unbearable agony. Clara darts for the man to save him with her healing touch—but so does her sister! The girls exchange confused glances.

This is the story of a thief girl who has chosen her own past, ceased to be the instrument of blind fate, and refashioned herself into a free miracle-worker.
@210
THE PATH OF LOGIC

Clara wakes up. Could the dream have been prophetic? She has prophetic dreams often, she's no longer surprised by them—she knows they are sent by the powers that want to warn the herald of what the future holds for her. There were a lot of clues hinting at the veracity of the message.

She does indeed know how to treat those in pain with her miraculous hands. She is indeed willing to ease their suffering. She truly strives to do the right thing! She loves her fellow beings. The girl is eager to do good deeds even if that requires her to go through pain and hardships...

Changeling wakes up at the edge of a pit in the ground. Sleep hasn't brought her comfort. Her back and her legs ache as though she has walked many miles. Her hands are covered in mud, there are traces of dried blood on her bare knees. It's dark. The dawn is a few hours away.
@211
"Allow me to remind you that an epidemic of unknown origin has already eradicated a few genuinely distinctive towns in the northern part of the country. The cause and circumstances of these tragic events remain uncertain. There is a lot that we cannot explain yet.

It appears as though the plague has a mind of its own, as if it is driven by some irrepressible will. Why else has no one managed to fight it successfully? Why does it target the most precious aspects of our existence? The Sand Plague picks its victims fastidiously—and the same principle always draws it back to whoever tries to oppose it. 

Surprisingly, we've yet to hear a single word from the Powers That Be."

[from H. Orff's internal note]
@212
"Traces of the supernatural reveal themselves more often than intelligent and reasonable men would prefer them to. Chimeras worshipped by our ancestors centuries ago crawl back into the light from ancient times. The directors of our fate rain ash down on us from the grey heavens.
<...>
They conceal themselves beneath us, above us, and among us, staying hidden until we muster up the resolve to meet their malevolent gaze. Having been discovered, they appear in the flesh for a mere moment—and then they expire horribly, wreaking havoc on the world that they rightfully see as their toy."
[Abv. XLII-b.14]
@213
This character is only unlocked after you've finished the Bachelor's or the Haruspex's storyline.
@300
Day One,
in which the Haruspex turns from a rightful heir into a dangerous criminal.
@301
Day Two,
in which the Haruspex under any circumstances gains more than he loses—for the first and the last time.
@302
Day Three,
in which the Haruspex uncovers the intricacies of the secret Steppe code at a great personal risk.
@303
Day Four,
by the end of which the Haruspex makes a friend and finds the half-dead enemy.
@304
Day Five,
in which the Haruspex gets a chance to grab Her Highness the Elusive Sand Plague by the tail.
@305
Day Six,
by the end of which the Haruspex finds out just how important a role mythical creatures can play in our lives.
@306
Day Seven,
fateful—which is to say, crucial and life-changing—for the Haruspex.
@307
Day Eight,
in which the Haruspex gets the idea of who He Who Was Marked by the Secret Sign may be.
@308
Day Nine,
in which it becomes apparent that the Haruspex will have to fight for the Kin and the land of his ancestors.
@309
Day Ten,
in which it becomes apparent that the Haruspex's victory will be defined by him making the right choice.
@310
Day Eleven,
in which the Haruspex finds himself trapped, for his dilemma consists of mutually exclusive truths.
@311
Day Twelve,
in which it finally becomes apparent what it was all about.
@312
Day One,
by the end of which the Bachelor finds himself battling a truly unvanquishable foe.
@313
Day Two,
in which the Bachelor gets to restructure authority as an equal and accept emergency powers.
@314
Day Three,
in which the Bachelor is offered to hunt the elusive enemy and evaluate the chances of necrosis.
@315
Day Four,
by the end of which the Bachelor realizes that the town is unprepared for an epidemic of this scale.
@316
Day Five,
in which the Bachelor regrets his affection for the living and would very much prefer to like the dead.
@317
Day Six,
in which the Bachelor is offered several possible sources of the infection to choose at his discretion.
@318
Day Seven,
in which the Bachelor gets a chance to uncover the truth and find an invaluable ally.
@319
Day Eight,
by the end of which the Bachelor can prove once again that the Earth is never up to any good.
@320
Day Nine,
in which the town is occupied and the worried children ask for the Bachelor's help for the first time ever.
@321
Day Ten,
in which the creators of the impossible take the stage to discuss captured miracles.
@322
Day Eleven,
in which the Kains' mission reveals its new and quite unexpected aspects to the Bachelor.
@323
Day Twelve,
in which it finally becomes apparent what it was all about.
@324
Day One,
in which the Changeling finally finds her sister, thus confirming the prophecy of the twin angels.
@325
Day Two,
in which the Changeling discovers her just judge skills, simultaneously converting into the true faith.
@326
Day Three,
in which the Changeling endeavours to hunt her impudent sister down and uncover habitual villains' sins.
@327
Day Four,
by the end of which it becomes apparent to the Changeling that someone is twisting her good deeds.
@328
Day Five,
which leads the Changeling to the conclusion that a peculiar mystery play-like event occurs in the town daily.
@329
Day Six,
fateful for the Changeling, who loses everything in the beginning, but gains a lot by the end of it.
@330
Day Seven,
in which the Changeling confirms her sainthood once again and sees the demons gang up on her.
@331
Day Eight,
in which the Changeling traces it all back to the source and realizes that the town desperately needs a true Mistress.
@332
Day Nine,
in which the Changeling finds out that in her case a thief and a miracle-worker are not necessarily the same thing.
@333
Day Ten,
in which Clara deciphers the hidden purpose of her miracles and the Changeling accepts the inevitability of death.
@334
Day Eleven,
in which the Changeling realizes the true meaning of her name and Clara loses the right to exist.
@335
Day Twelve,
in which it becomes possible to do the impossible.
@350
The night has come. The most pressing endeavours of the day were fulfilled at the expense of several lives of your Bound. A mime performance at the Theatre will feature today's events.
@351
The day is over. Your timely efforts allowed your supporters to remain unharmed. A new mime performance is being rehearsed at the Theatre.
@400
An empty bottle is required.
@401
The inhabitant of this place is sick.
@402
The inhabitant of this place is dead.
@403
Locked.
@500	; save/load menu, short player name
Bachelor
@501	; save/load menu, short player name
Haruspex
@502	; save/load menu, short player name
Changeling
@503	; save/load menu, for saved games made during intro scene
(Intro)
@504
(Ending)
@550
The morning of the second day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends in less than eleven days.
@551
The morning of the third day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends in less than ten days.
@552
The morning of the fourth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

The Powers That Be are getting increasingly worried. It all ends in less than nine days.
@553
The morning of the fifth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

You cannot fight this. It all ends in less than eight days.
@554
The morning of the sixth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends in less than seven days. The emissary arrives tomorrow.
@555
The morning of the seventh day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

Even an Inquisitor will not help you defeat this enemy. It all ends in less than six days.
@556
The morning of the eighth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends in less than five days. The army arrives tomorrow.
@557
The morning of the ninth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

The town is dying. It all ends in less than four days.
@558
The morning of the tenth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends in less than three days.

@559
The morning of the eleventh day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

It all ends tomorrow.
@560
The morning of the twelfth day has come.

Infected yesterday: %d ppl.
Died yesterday: %d ppl.
Gone missing: %d ppl.
Total death toll: %d ppl.
Currently infected: %d ppl.

Today is the final day. You have less than fourteen hours to make the right choice.

@600
Ice-Pick Lodge Studios

The Classic HD Edition Team

Alexandra “Alphyna” Golubeva
Nikolay Dybowski
Vassily Kashnikov
Masha Khomenko
Evgeny Leutin
Meethos
Igor Pokrovsky
Peter Potapov
Ivan Slovtsov
Ayrat Zakirov


The Original Pathologic Team

Alexey Bakhvalov (Lead Programmer)
Nikolay Dybowski (Head of the Laboratory)
Vlad Ermakov (3D Modelling)
Andriesh Gandrabur (Composer/Sound Design)
Vyacheslav Goncharenko (3D Modelling)
Groan (Art Director)
Irina Kapitonova (Artist)
Meethos (Lead Artist)
Peter Potapov (3D Design)
Ekaterina Romashkina (Animation)
Ayrat Zakirov (CTO)


The simulator was made possible 
with the kind help of

Ivan Bunakov
Alexander Emelianov
Maxim Fomin
Artemy Kalinin
Alexander Nikitin
Kirill Savenko
Ilya Stepanov


The heavy renewal lifting
was done by GENERAL ARCADE

Gennadiy Potapov (Project Manager / Programmer)
Anton Savinov (Graphic Designer)
Serge Shubin (Lead Programmer)
Baurjan Sitkaliev (UI Adaptation)


English Localization Lead

Alexandra “Alphyna” Golubeva


English Localization Team

Groan
Yaroslav Golubev
Nikolay Ershov
Nikolay Konovalenko
Alexander Kuvshinnikov
Ivan Lyukov
Jake Milner
Alice Tomina


Italian Localization Team

Stefano Gaburri
Claudio Todeschini


Polish Localization Team

Jakub Derdziak (translation)
Aldona Derdziak (proofreading)


The HD release was made possible
with the assistance of

Georgiy Cherkalin
Richard Cook
Elena Erofeeva
Gorn Knizhnik
Yaroslav Kravtsov
Liu
Scott McLesley
Maksar Shipkhineev
Alexander Tishin
Nikita Varnakov
Sofia Vasilenko

Devolver Digital


HD Classic Edition Testing

Karina Akhmetvalieva
Asya Aleshkina
Sergey Bubenov
Kirill Kazalainen
Vassily “Anmoris” Krasilnikov
Dmitry Michelev
Elizaveta Orlovskaya
Nadezhda Sennikova
Vladislav Smolnikov “Zavatsky”
Vladimir Spartakovich
Olga Strizh
Alexey Sudakov
Andrey Tishin
Vladimir Venevitinov 
Lara Voskresenskaya


Special Thanks

Anastasia
Andrey Batukhanov
Semen Brodetsky
Anna Cheremukhina
Valeria Chikina
Alexandra Dashina
Valery Dolzhenkov
Vladimir Dybowski
Varda Golovanova
Sasha Khalikov
Lera Kim
Nikita Koledin
Olga Komissarova
Gennady Kozlov
Yulia Loginova
Tomas Motskus
Lisa Nikonova
Viola Novikova
Nikita Preksin
Yuri Reiser
Artem Rybakov
Marina Sarycheva
Victor Solovyev
Kirill Sosnovsky
Natalia Shornikova
Marina Titareva
Fedor Voskresensky
Natalia Vremyachkina


The Most Special Thanks Of All

Gaukhar Aldiyarova
Kirill Bestemyanov
Ruslan Dmitriev
Alexey Pastushenko
Igor Pokrovsky


English Voicing Director

Asya Chashchinskaya


English Voice Actors

Titus Adam
Daniel Barnes
Martin Cooke
Rob Corpuz
Bruce Grant
Leadie Flowers
Jordan Fry
Asya Lobanova
Jacqueline Vouga


Russian Voice Actors

Kostya Abramov
Olga Krasko
Dmitry Polonsky
Rogvold Sukhoverko
Nadezhda Ushanova
Sasha Fisenko
Victoria Fisher
Andrey Yaroslavtsev


Gambitious/Devolver Digital

Andrew Parsons
Andy Payne
Brian Grigsby
Doug Johns
Graeme Struthers
Harry Miller
John Bartkiw
Justin Burnham
Kate Ludlow
Kool Things
Mike Wilson
Nick Todd
Nigel Lowrie
Paul Hanraets
Richard Cook
Robbie Paterson
Rodrigo Batelli
Scott Alexander
Sjoerd Geurts
Vernon Vrolijk


The Cosmocover Team

Brolima
Chris
Fabian
John
Philémon
Pilou Rebeca
Nyssa


The Evolve Team

Brian Rowe
Candace Ohle
Matt Broitman
Tom Ohle

Willard Public Affairs


Kool Things

Testronic
@700 ; playerstat window
Reputation
@701 ; playerstat window, dream window
Health
@702 ; playerstat window, dream window
Immunity
@703 ; playerstat window, dream window
Hunger
@704 ; playerstat window, dream window
Exhaustion
@705 ; playerstat window, dream window
Infection
@706 ; playerstat window
Blow Softening
@707 ; playerstat window
Protection from Bullets
@708 ; playerstat window
Protection from Fire
@709 ; playerstat window
Protection from Infection
@710 ; playerstat window
Bodily Functions
@711 ; playerstat window
Outfit
@712 ; playerstat window
Time
@713 ; playerstat window
Artemy Burakh
@714 ; playerstat window
Daniil Dankovsky
@715 ; playerstat window
Clara
@725 ; agony
Pain
@1000
Pathologic
@1001
Error initializing "LifeStudio: HEAD"
@1002
Error creating sound system, game will run without sound
@1003
Failed to initialize video system
@1004
Error creating renderer. Press OK to run configuration utility.
@1005
Error creating user interface
@1006
Number of uses:
@1007
Repair cost: